Act III

Scene I

Before Prospero’s cell.

Enter Ferdinand, bearing a log.
Ferdinand |

There be some sports are painful, and their labour
Delight in them sets off: some kinds of baseness
Are nobly undergone and most poor matters
Point to rich ends. This my mean task
Would be as heavy to me as odious, but
The mistress which I serve quickens what’s dead
And makes my labours pleasures: O, she is
Ten times more gentle than her father’s crabbed,
And he’s composed of harshness. I must remove
Some thousands of these logs and pile them up,
Upon a sore injunction: my sweet mistress
Weeps when she sees me work, and says, such baseness
Had never like executor. I forget:
But these sweet thoughts do even refresh my labours,
Most busy lest, when I do it.

Enter Miranda; and Prospero at a distance, unseen.
Miranda |

Alas, now, pray you,
Work not so hard: I would the lightning had
Burnt up those logs that you are enjoin’d to pile!
Pray, set it down and rest you: when this burns,
’Twill weep for having wearied you. My father
Is hard at study; pray now, rest yourself;
He’s safe for these three hours.

Ferdinand |

O most dear mistress,
The sun will set before I shall discharge
What I must strive to do.

Miranda |

If you’ll sit down,
I’ll bear your logs the while: pray, give me that;
I’ll carry it to the pile.

Ferdinand |

No, precious creature;
I had rather crack my sinews, break my back,
Than you should such dishonour undergo,
While I sit lazy by.

Miranda |

It would become me
As well as it does you: and I should do it
With much more ease; for my good will is to it,
And yours it is against.

Prospero |

Poor worm, thou art infected!
This visitation shows it.

Miranda | You look wearily.
Ferdinand |

No, noble mistress; ’tis fresh morning with me
When you are by at night. I do beseech you—
Chiefly that I might set it in my prayers—
What is your name?

Miranda |

Miranda.—O my father,
I have broke your hest to say so!

Ferdinand |

Admired Miranda!
Indeed the top of admiration! worth
What’s dearest to the world! Full many a lady
I have eyed with best regard and many a time
The harmony of their tongues hath into bondage
Brought my too diligent ear: for several virtues
Have I liked several women; never any
With so fun soul, but some defect in her
Did quarrel with the noblest grace she owed
And put it to the foil: but you, O you,
So perfect and so peerless, are created
Of every creature’s best!

Miranda |

I do not know
One of my sex; no woman’s face remember,
Save, from my glass, mine own; nor have I seen
More that I may call men than you, good friend,
And my dear father: how features are abroad,
I am skilless of; but, by my modesty,
The jewel in my dower, I would not wish
Any companion in the world but you,
Nor can imagination form a shape,
Besides yourself, to like of. But I prattle
Something too wildly and my father’s precepts
I therein do forget.

Ferdinand |

I am in my condition
A prince, Miranda; I do think, a king;
I would, not so!—and would no more endure
This wooden slavery than to suffer
The flesh-fly blow my mouth. Hear my soul speak:
The very instant that I saw you, did
My heart fly to your service; there resides,
To make me slave to it; and for your sake
Am I this patient log-man.

Miranda | Do you love me?
Ferdinand |

O heaven, O earth, bear witness to this sound
And crown what I profess with kind event
If I speak true! if hollowly, invert
What best is boded me to mischief! I
Beyond all limit of what else i’ the world
Do love, prize, honour you.

Miranda |

I am a fool
To weep at what I am glad of.

Prospero |

Fair encounter
Of two most rare affections! Heavens rain grace
On that which breeds between ’em!

Ferdinand | Wherefore weep you?
Miranda |

At mine unworthiness that dare not offer
What I desire to give, and much less take
What I shall die to want. But this is trifling;
And all the more it seeks to hide itself,
The bigger bulk it shows. Hence, bashful cunning!
And prompt me, plain and holy innocence!
I am your wife, if you will marry me;
If not, I’ll die your maid: to be your fellow
You may deny me; but I’ll be your servant,
Whether you will or no.

Ferdinand |

My mistress, dearest;
And I thus humble ever.

Miranda | My husband, then?
Ferdinand |

Ay, with a heart as willing
As bondage e’er of freedom: here’s my hand.

Miranda |

And mine, with my heart in’t: and now farewell
Till half an hour hence.

Ferdinand | A thousand thousand!
Exeunt Ferdinand and Miranda severally.
Prospero |

So glad of this as they I cannot be,
Who are surprised withal; but my rejoicing
At nothing can be more. I’ll to my book,
For yet ere supper-time must I perform
Much business appertaining. Exit.

Scene II

Another part of the island.

Enter Caliban, Stephano, and Trinculo.
Stephano | Tell not me; when the butt is out, we will drink water; not a drop before: therefore bear up, and board ’em. Servant-monster, drink to me.
Trinculo | Servant-monster! the folly of this island! They say there’s but five upon this isle: we are three of them; if th’ other two be brained like us, the state totters.
Stephano | Drink, servant-monster, when I bid thee: thy eyes are almost set in thy head.
Trinculo | Where should they be set else? he were a brave monster indeed, if they were set in his tail.
Stephano | My man-monster hath drown’d his tongue in sack: for my part, the sea cannot drown me; I swam, ere I could recover the shore, five and thirty leagues off and on. By this light, thou shalt be my lieutenant, monster, or my standard.
Trinculo | Your lieutenant, if you list; he’s no standard.
Stephano | We’ll not run, Monsieur Monster.
Trinculo | Nor go neither; but you’ll lie like dogs and yet say nothing neither.
Stephano | Moon-calf, speak once in thy life, if thou beest a good moon-calf.
Caliban |

How does thy honour? Let me lick thy shoe.
I’ll not serve him; he’s not valiant.

Trinculo | Thou liest, most ignorant monster: I am in case to justle a constable. Why, thou deboshed fish thou, was there ever man a coward that hath drunk so much sack as I to-day? Wilt thou tell a monstrous lie, being but half a fish and half a monster?
Caliban | Lo, how he mocks me! wilt thou let him, my lord?
Trinculo | “Lord” quoth he! That a monster should be such a natural!
Caliban | Lo, lo, again! bite him to death, I prithee.
Stephano | Trinculo, keep a good tongue in your head: if you prove a mutineer,—the next tree! The poor monster’s my subject and he shall not suffer indignity.
Caliban | I thank my noble lord. Wilt thou be pleased to hearken once again to the suit I made to thee?
Stephano | Marry, will I: kneel and repeat it; I will stand, and so shall Trinculo.
Enter Ariel, invisible
Caliban | As I told thee before, I am subject to a tyrant, a sorcerer, that by his cunning hath cheated me of the island.
Ariel | Thou liest.
Caliban |

Thou liest, thou jesting monkey, thou:
I would my valiant master would destroy thee!
I do not lie.

Stephano | Trinculo, if you trouble him any more in’s tale, by this hand, I will supplant some of your teeth.
Trinculo | Why, I said nothing.
Stephano | Mum, then, and no more. Proceed.
Caliban |

I say, by sorcery he got this isle;
From me he got it. If thy greatness will
Revenge it on him,—for I know thou darest,
But this thing dare not,—

Stephano | That’s most certain.
Caliban | Thou shalt be lord of it and I’ll serve thee.
Stephano | How now shall this be compassed? Canst thou bring me to the party?
Caliban |

Yea, yea, my lord: I’ll yield him thee asleep,
Where thou mayst knock a nail into his head.

Ariel | Thou liest; thou canst not.
Caliban |

What a pied ninny’s this! Thou scurvy patch!
I do beseech thy greatness, give him blows
And take his bottle from him: when that’s gone
He shall drink nought but brine; for I’ll not show him
Where the quick freshes are.

Stephano | Trinculo, run into no further danger: interrupt the monster one word further, and, by this hand, I’ll turn my mercy out o’ doors and make a stock-fish of thee.
Trinculo | Why, what did I? I did nothing. I’ll go farther off.
Stephano | Didst thou not say he lied?
Ariel | Thou liest.
Stephano | Do I so? take thou that. Beats Trinculo. As you like this, give me the lie another time.
Trinculo | I did not give the lie. Out o’ your wits and hearing too? A pox o’ your bottle! this can sack and drinking do. A murrain on your monster, and the devil take your fingers!
Caliban | Ha, ha, ha!
Stephano | Now, forward with your tale. Prithee, stand farther off.
Caliban |

Beat him enough: after a little time
I’ll beat him too.

Stephano | Stand farther. Come, proceed.
Caliban |

Why, as I told thee, ’tis a custom with him,
I’ th’ afternoon to sleep: there thou mayst brain him,
Having first seized his books, or with a log
Batter his skull, or paunch him with a stake,
Or cut his wezand with thy knife. Remember
First to possess his books; for without them
He’s but a sot, as I am, nor hath not
One spirit to command: they all do hate him
As rootedly as I. Burn but his books.
He has brave utensils,—for so he calls them,—
Which when he has a house, he’ll deck withal.
And that most deeply to consider is
The beauty of his daughter; he himself
Calls her a nonpareil: I never saw a woman,
But only Sycorax my dam and she;
But she as far surpasseth Sycorax
As great’st does least.

Stephano | Is it so brave a lass?
Caliban |

Ay, lord; she will become thy bed, I warrant.
And bring thee forth brave brood.

Stephano | Monster, I will kill this man: his daughter and I will be king and queen,—save our graces!—and Trinculo and thyself shall be viceroys. Dost thou like the plot, Trinculo?
Trinculo | Excellent.
Stephano | Give me thy hand: I am sorry I beat thee; but, while thou livest, keep a good tongue in thy head.
Caliban |

Within this half hour will he be asleep:
Wilt thou destroy him then?

Stephano | Ay, on mine honour.
Ariel | This will I tell my master.
Caliban |

Thou makest me merry; I am full of pleasure:
Let us be jocund: will you troll the catch
You taught me but while-ere?

Stephano | At thy request, monster, I will do reason, any reason. Come on, Trinculo, let us sing. Sings.

Flout ’em and scout ’em
And scout ’em and flout ’em;
Thought is free.

Caliban | That’s not the tune. Ariel plays the tune on a tabor and pipe.
Stephano | What is this same?
Trinculo | This is the tune of our catch, played by the picture of Nobody.
Stephano | If thou beest a man, show thyself in thy likeness: if thou beest a devil, take’t as thou list.
Trinculo | O, forgive me my sins!
Stephano | He that dies pays all debts: I defy thee. Mercy upon us!
Caliban | Art thou afeard?
Stephano | No, monster, not I.
Caliban |

Be not afeard; the isle is full of noises,
Sounds and sweet airs, that give delight and hurt not.
Sometimes a thousand twangling instruments
Will hum about mine ears, and sometime voices
That, if I then had waked after long sleep,
Will make me sleep again: and then, in dreaming,
The clouds methought would open and show riches
Ready to drop upon me, that, when I waked,
I cried to dream again.

Stephano | This will prove a brave kingdom to me, where I shall have my music for nothing.
Caliban | When Prospero is destroyed.
Stephano | That shall be by and by: I remember the story.
Trinculo | The sound is going away; let’s follow it, and after do our work.
Stephano | Lead, monster; we’ll follow. I would I could see this tabourer; he lays it on.
Trinculo | Wilt come? I’ll follow, Stephano. Exeunt.

Scene III

Another part of the island.

Enter Alonso, Sebastian, Antonio, Gonzalo, Adrian, Francisco, and others.
Gonzalo |

By’r lakin, I can go no further, sir;
My old bones ache: here’s a maze trod indeed
Through forth-rights and meanders! By your patience,
I needs must rest me.

Alonso |

Old lord, I cannot blame thee,
Who am myself attach’d with weariness,
To the dulling of my spirits: sit down, and rest.
Even here I will put off my hope and keep it
No longer for my flatterer: he is drown’d
Whom thus we stray to find, and the sea mocks
Our frustrate search on land. Well, let him go.

Antonio |

Aside to Sebastian. I am right glad that he’s so out of hope.
Do not, for one repulse, forego the purpose
That you resolved to effect.

Sebastian |

Aside to Antonio. The next advantage
Will we take throughly.

Antonio |

Aside to Sebastian. Let it be to-night;
For, now they are oppress’d with travel, they
Will not, nor cannot, use such vigilance
As when they are fresh.

Sebastian | Aside to Antonio. I say, to-night: no more. Solemn and strange music.
Alonso | What harmony is this? My good friends, hark!
Gonzalo | Marvellous sweet music!
Enter Prospero above, invisible. Enter several strange Shapes, bringing in a banquet; they dance about it with gentle actions of salutation; and, inviting the King, etc. to eat, they depart.
Alonso | Give us kind keepers, heavens! What were these?
Sebastian |

A living drollery. Now I will believe
That there are unicorns, that in Arabia
There is one tree, the phoenix’ throne, one phoenix
At this hour reigning there.

Antonio |

I’ll believe both;
And what does else want credit, come to me,
And I’ll be sworn ’tis true: travellers ne’er did lie,
Though fools at home condemn ’em.

Gonzalo |

If in Naples
I should report this now, would they believe me?
If I should say, I saw such islanders—
For, certes, these are people of the island—
Who, though they are of monstrous shape, yet, note,
Their manners are more gentle-kind than of
Our human generation you shall find
Many, nay, almost any.

Prospero |

Aside Honest lord,
Thou hast said well; for some of you there present
Are worse than devils.

Alonso |

I cannot too much muse
Such shapes, such gesture and such sound, expressing,
Although they want the use of tongue, a kind
Of excellent dumb discourse.

Prospero | Aside Praise in departing.
Francisco | They vanish’d strangely.
Sebastian |

No matter, since
They have left their viands behind; for we have stomachs.
Will’t please you taste of what is here?

Alonso | Not I.
Gonzalo |

Faith, sir, you need not fear. When we were boys,
Who would believe that there were mountaineers
Dew-lapp’d like bulls, whose throats had hanging at ’em
Wallets of flesh? or that there were such men
Whose heads stood in their breasts? which now we find
Each putter-out of five for one will bring us
Good warrant of.

Alonso |

I will stand to and feed,
Although my last: no matter, since I feel
The best is past. Brother, my lord the duke,
Stand to and do as we.

Thunder and lightning. Enter Ariel, like a harpy; claps his wings upon the table; and, with a quaint device, the banquet vanishes.
Ariel |

You are three men of sin, whom Destiny,
That hath to instrument this lower world
And what is in’t, the never-surfeited sea
Hath caused to belch up you; and on this island
Where man doth not inhabit; you ’mongst men
Being most unfit to live. I have made you mad;
And even with such-like valour men hang and drown
Their proper selves. Alonso, Sebastian etc. draw their swords. You fools! I and my fellows
Are ministers of Fate: the elements,
Of whom your swords are temper’d, may as well
Wound the loud winds, or with bemock’d-at stabs
Kill the still-closing waters, as diminish
One dowle that’s in my plume: my fellow-ministers
Are like invulnerable. If you could hurt,
Your swords are now too massy for your strengths
And will not be uplifted. But remember—
For that’s my business to you—that you three
From Milan did supplant good Prospero;
Exposed unto the sea, which hath requit it,
Him and his innocent child: for which foul deed
The powers, delaying, not forgetting, have
Incensed the seas and shores, yea, all the creatures,
Against your peace. Thee of thy son, Alonso,
They have bereft; and do pronounce by me
Lingering perdition, worse than any death
Can be at once, shall step by step attend
You and your ways; whose wraths to guard you from—
Which here, in this most desolate isle, else falls
Upon your heads—is nothing but heart-sorrow
And a clear life ensuing.

He vanishes in thunder; then, to soft music enter the Shapes again, and dance, with mocks and mows, and carrying out the table.
Prospero |

Bravely the figure of this harpy hast thou
Perform’d, my Ariel; a grace it had, devouring:
Of my instruction hast thou nothing bated
In what thou hadst to say: so, with good life
And observation strange, my meaner ministers
Their several kinds have done. My high charms work
And these mine enemies are all knit up
In their distractions; they now are in my power;
And in these fits I leave them, while I visit
Young Ferdinand, whom they suppose is drown’d,
And his and mine loved darling. Exit above.

Gonzalo |

I’ the name of something holy, sir, why stand you
In this strange stare?

Alonso |

O, it is monstrous, monstrous!
Methought the billows spoke and told me of it;
The winds did sing it to me, and the thunder,
That deep and dreadful organ-pipe, pronounced
The name of Prosper: it did bass my trespass.
Therefore my son i’ the ooze is bedded, and
I’ll seek him deeper than e’er plummet sounded
And with him there lie mudded. Exit.

Sebastian |

But one fiend at a time,
I’ll fight their legions o’er.

Antonio | I’ll be thy second. Exeunt Sebastian, and Antonio.
Gonzalo |

All three of them are desperate: their great guilt,
Like poison given to work a great time after,
Now ’gins to bite the spirits. I do beseech you
That are of suppler joints, follow them swiftly
And hinder them from what this ecstasy
May now provoke them to.

Adrian | Follow, I pray you. Exeunt.

Act V

Scene I

Before Prospero’s cell.

Enter Prospero in his magic robes, and Ariel.
Prospero |

Now does my project gather to a head:
My charms crack not; my spirits obey; and time
Goes upright with his carriage. How’s the day?

Ariel |

On the sixth hour; at which time, my lord,
You said our work should cease.

Prospero |

I did say so,
When first I raised the tempest. Say, my spirit,
How fares the king and’s followers?

Ariel |

Confined together
In the same fashion as you gave in charge,
Just as you left them; all prisoners, sir,
In the line-grove which weather-fends your cell;
They cannot budge till your release. The king,
His brother and yours, abide all three distracted
And the remainder mourning over them,
Brimful of sorrow and dismay; but chiefly
Him that you term’d, sir, “The good old lord Gonzalo;”
His tears run down his beard, like winter’s drops
From eaves of reeds. Your charm so strongly works ’em
That if you now beheld them, your affections
Would become tender.

Prospero | Dost thou think so, spirit?
Ariel | Mine would, sir, were I human.
Prospero |

And mine shall.
Hast thou, which art but air, a touch, a feeling
Of their afflictions, and shall not myself,
One of their kind, that relish all as sharply,
Passion as they, be kindlier moved than thou art?
Though with their high wrongs I am struck to the quick,
Yet with my nobler reason ’gainst my fury
Do I take part: the rarer action is
In virtue than in vengeance: they being penitent,
The sole drift of my purpose doth extend
Not a frown further. Go release them, Ariel:
My charms I’ll break, their senses I’ll restore,
And they shall be themselves.

Ariel | I’ll fetch them, sir. Exit.
Prospero |

Ye elves of hills, brooks, standing lakes and groves,
And ye that on the sands with printless foot
Do chase the ebbing Neptune and do fly him
When he comes back; you demi-puppets that
By moonshine do the green sour ringlets make,
Whereof the ewe not bites, and you whose pastime
Is to make midnight mushrooms, that rejoice
To hear the solemn curfew; by whose aid,
Weak masters though ye be, I have bedimm’d
The noontide sun, call’d forth the mutinous winds,
And ’twixt the green sea and the azured vault
Set roaring war: to the dread rattling thunder
Have I given fire and rifted Jove’s stout oak
With his own bolt; the strong-based promontory
Have I made shake and by the spurs pluck’d up
The pine and cedar: graves at my command
Have waked their sleepers, oped, and let ’em forth
By my so potent art. But this rough magic
I here abjure, and, when I have required
Some heavenly music, which even now I do,
To work mine end upon their senses that
This airy charm is for, I’ll break my staff,
Bury it certain fathoms in the earth,
And deeper than did ever plummet sound
I’ll drown my book. Solemn music.

Re-enter Ariel before: then Alonso, with a frantic gesture, attended by Gonzalo; Sebastian and Antonio in like manner, attended by Adrian and Francisco they all enter the circle which Prospero had made, and there stand charmed; which Prospero observing, speaks:

A solemn air and the best comforter
To an unsettled fancy cure thy brains,
Now useless, boil’d within thy skull! There stand,
For you are spell-stopp’d.
Holy Gonzalo, honourable man,
Mine eyes, even sociable to the show of thine,
Fall fellowly drops. The charm dissolves apace,
And as the morning steals upon the night,
Melting the darkness, so their rising senses
Begin to chase the ignorant fumes that mantle
Their clearer reason. O good Gonzalo,
My true preserver, and a loyal sir
To him you follow’st! I will pay thy graces
Home both in word and deed. Most cruelly
Didst thou, Alonso, use me and my daughter:
Thy brother was a furtherer in the act.
Thou art pinch’d fort now, Sebastian. Flesh and blood,
You, brother mine, that entertain’d ambition,
Expell’d remorse and nature; who, with Sebastian,
Whose inward pinches therefore are most strong,
Would here have kill’d your king; I do forgive thee,
Unnatural though thou art. Their understanding
Begins to swell, and the approaching tide
Will shortly fill the reasonable shore
That now lies foul and muddy. Not one of them
That yet looks on me, or would know me: Ariel,
Fetch me the hat and rapier in my cell:
I will discase me, and myself present
As I was sometime Milan: quickly, spirit;
Thou shalt ere long be free.

Ariel sings and helps to attire him.

Where the bee sucks, there suck I:
In a cowslip’s bell I lie;
There I couch when owls do cry.
On the bat’s back I do fly
After summer merrily.
Merrily, merrily shall I live now
Under the blossom that hangs on the bough.

Prospero |

Why, that’s my dainty Ariel! I shall miss thee;
But yet thou shalt have freedom: so, so, so.
To the king’s ship, invisible as thou art:
There shalt thou find the mariners asleep
Under the hatches; the master and the boatswain
Being awake, enforce them to this place,
And presently, I prithee.

Ariel |

I drink the air before me, and return
Or ere your pulse twice beat. Exit.

Gonzalo |

All torment, trouble, wonder and amazement
Inhabits here: some heavenly power guide us
Out of this fearful country!

Prospero |

Behold, sir king,
The wronged Duke of Milan, Prospero:
For more assurance that a living prince
Does now speak to thee, I embrace thy body;
And to thee and thy company I bid
A hearty welcome.

Alonso |

Whether thou best he or no,
Or some enchanted trifle to abuse me,
As late I have been, I not know: thy pulse
Beats as of flesh and blood; and, since I saw thee,
The affliction of my mind amends, with which,
I fear, a madness held me: this must crave,
An if this be at all, a most strange story.
Thy dukedom I resign and do entreat
Thou pardon me my wrongs. But how should Prospero
Be living and be here?

Prospero |

First, noble friend,
Let me embrace thine age, whose honour cannot
Be measured or confined.

Gonzalo |

Whether this be
Or be not, I’ll not swear.

Prospero |

You do yet taste
Some subtilties o’ the isle, that will not let you
Believe things certain. Welcome, my friends all!
Aside to Sebastian and Antonio. But you, my brace of lords, were I so minded,
I here could pluck his highness’ frown upon you
And justify you traitors: at this time
I will tell no tales.

Sebastian | Aside The devil speaks in him.
Prospero |

No.
For you, most wicked sir, whom to call brother
Would even infect my mouth, I do forgive
Thy rankest fault; all of them; and require
My dukedom of thee, which perforce, I know,
Thou must restore.

Alonso |

If thou be’st Prospero,
Give us particulars of thy preservation;
How thou hast met us here, who three hours since
Were wreck’d upon this shore; where I have lost—
How sharp the point of this remembrance is!—
My dear son Ferdinand.

Prospero | I am woe for’t, sir.
Alonso |

Irreparable is the loss, and patience
Says it is past her cure.

Prospero |

I rather think
You have not sought her help, of whose soft grace
For the like loss I have her sovereign aid
And rest myself content.

Alonso | You the like loss!
Prospero |

As great to me as late; and, supportable
To make the dear loss, have I means much weaker
Than you may call to comfort you, for I
Have lost my daughter.

Alonso |

A daughter?
O heavens, that they were living both in Naples,
The king and queen there! that they were, I wish
Myself were mudded in that oozy bed
Where my son lies. When did you lose your daughter?

Prospero |

In this last tempest. I perceive, these lords
At this encounter do so much admire
That they devour their reason and scarce think
Their eyes do offices of truth, their words
Are natural breath: but, howsoe’er you have
Been justled from your senses, know for certain
That I am Prospero and that very duke
Which was thrust forth of Milan, who most strangely
Upon this shore, where you were wreck’d, was landed,
To be the lord on’t. No more yet of this;
For ’tis a chronicle of day by day,
Not a relation for a breakfast nor
Befitting this first meeting. Welcome, sir;
This cell’s my court: here have I few attendants
And subjects none abroad: pray you, look in.
My dukedom since you have given me again,
I will requite you with as good a thing;
At least bring forth a wonder, to content ye
As much as me my dukedom.

Here Prospero discovers Ferdinand and Miranda playing at chess.
Miranda | Sweet lord, you play me false.
Ferdinand |

No, my dear’st love,
I would not for the world.

Miranda |

Yes, for a score of kingdoms you should wrangle,
And I would call it, fair play.

Alonso |

If this prove
A vision of the Island, one dear son
Shall I twice lose.

Sebastian | A most high miracle!
Ferdinand |

Though the seas threaten, they are merciful;
I have cursed them without cause. Kneels.

Alonso |

Now all the blessings
Of a glad father compass thee about!
Arise, and say how thou camest here.

Miranda |

O, wonder!
How many goodly creatures are there here!
How beauteous mankind is! O brave new world,
That has such people in’t!

Prospero | ’Tis new to thee.
Alonso |

What is this maid with whom thou wast at play?
Your eld’st acquaintance cannot be three hours:
Is she the goddess that hath sever’d us,
And brought us thus together?

Ferdinand |

Sir, she is mortal;
But by immortal Providence she’s mine:
I chose her when I could not ask my father
For his advice, nor thought I had one. She
Is daughter to this famous Duke of Milan,
Of whom so often I have heard renown,
But never saw before; of whom I have
Received a second life; and second father
This lady makes him to me.

Alonso |

I am hers:
But, O, how oddly will it sound that I
Must ask my child forgiveness!

Prospero |

There, sir, stop:
Let us not burthen our remembrance with
A heaviness that’s gone.

Gonzalo |

I have inly wept,
Or should have spoke ere this. Look down, you gods,
And on this couple drop a blessed crown!
For it is you that have chalk’d forth the way
Which brought us hither.

Alonso | I say, Amen, Gonzalo!
Gonzalo |

Was Milan thrust from Milan, that his issue
Should become kings of Naples? O, rejoice
Beyond a common joy, and set it down
With gold on lasting pillars: In one voyage
Did Claribel her husband find at Tunis,
And Ferdinand, her brother, found a wife
Where he himself was lost, Prospero his dukedom
In a poor isle and all of us ourselves
When no man was his own.

Alonso |

To Ferdinand and Miranda. Give me your hands:
Let grief and sorrow still embrace his heart
That doth not wish you joy!

Gonzalo | Be it so! Amen!
Re-enter Ariel, with the Master and Boatswain amazedly following.

O, look, sir, look, sir! here is more of us:
I prophesied, if a gallows were on land,
This fellow could not drown. Now, blasphemy,
That swear’st grace o’erboard, not an oath on shore?
Hast thou no mouth by land? What is the news?

Boatswain |

The best news is, that we have safely found
Our king and company; the next, our ship—
Which, but three glasses since, we gave out split—
Is tight and yare and bravely rigg’d as when
We first put out to sea.

Ariel |

Aside to Prospero. Sir, all this service
Have I done since I went.

Prospero | Aside to Ariel. My tricksy spirit!
Alonso |

These are not natural events; they strengthen
From strange to stranger. Say, how came you hither?

Boatswain |

If I did think, sir, I were well awake,
I’ld strive to tell you. We were dead of sleep,
And—how we know not—all clapp’d under hatches;
Where but even now with strange and several noises
Of roaring, shrieking, howling, jingling chains,
And moe diversity of sounds, all horrible,
We were awaked; straightway, at liberty;
Where we, in all her trim, freshly beheld
Our royal, good and gallant ship, our master
Capering to eye her: on a trice, so please you,
Even in a dream, were we divided from them
And were brought moping hither.

Ariel | Aside to Prospero. Was’t well done?
Prospero | Aside to Ariel. Bravely, my diligence. Thou shalt be free.
Alonso |

This is as strange a maze as e’er men trod;
And there is in this business more than nature
Was ever conduct of: some oracle
Must rectify our knowledge.

Prospero |

Sir, my liege,
Do not infest your mind with beating on
The strangeness of this business; at pick’d leisure
Which shall be shortly, single I’ll resolve you,
Which to you shall seem probable, of every
These happen’d accidents; till when, be cheerful
And think of each thing well. Aside to Ariel. Come hither, spirit:
Set Caliban and his companions free;
Untie the spell. Exit Ariel.
How fares my gracious sir?
There are yet missing of your company
Some few odd lads that you remember not.

Re-enter Ariel, driving in Caliban, Stephano and Trinculo, in their stolen apparel.
Stephano | Every man shift for all the rest, and let no man take care for himself; for all is but fortune. Coragio, bully-monster, coragio!
Trinculo | If these be true spies which I wear in my head, here’s a goodly sight.
Caliban |

O Setebos, these be brave spirits indeed!
How fine my master is! I am afraid
He will chastise me.

Sebastian |

Ha, ha!
What things are these, my lord Antonio?
Will money buy ’em?

Antonio |

Very like; one of them
Is a plain fish, and, no doubt, marketable.

Prospero |

Mark but the badges of these men, my lords,
Then say if they be true. This mis-shapen knave,
His mother was a witch, and one so strong
That could control the moon, make flows and ebbs,
And deal in her command without her power.
These three have robb’d me; and this demi-devil—
For he’s a bastard one—had plotted with them
To take my life. Two of these fellows you
Must know and own; this thing of darkness I
Acknowledge mine.

Caliban | I shall be pinch’d to death.
Alonso | Is not this Stephano, my drunken butler?
Sebastian | He is drunk now: where had he wine?
Alonso |

And Trinculo is reeling ripe: where should they
Find this grand liquor that hath gilded ’em?
How camest thou in this pickle?

Trinculo | I have been in such a pickle since I saw you last that, I fear me, will never out of my bones: I shall not fear fly-blowing.
Sebastian | Why, how now, Stephano!
Stephano | O, touch me not; I am not Stephano, but a cramp.
Prospero | You’ld be king o’ the isle, sirrah?
Stephano | I should have been a sore one then.
Alonso | This is a strange thing as e’er I look’d on. Pointing to Caliban.
Prospero |

He is as disproportion’d in his manners
As in his shape. Go, sirrah, to my cell;
Take with you your companions; as you look
To have my pardon, trim it handsomely.

Caliban |

Ay, that I will; and I’ll be wise hereafter
And seek for grace. What a thrice-double ass
Was I, to take this drunkard for a god
And worship this dull fool!

Prospero | Go to; away!
Alonso | Hence, and bestow your luggage where you found it.
Sebastian | Or stole it, rather. Exeunt Caliban, Stephano, and Trinculo.
Prospero |

Sir, I invite your highness and your train
To my poor cell, where you shall take your rest
For this one night; which, part of it, I’ll waste
With such discourse as, I not doubt, shall make it
Go quick away; the story of my life
And the particular accidents gone by
Since I came to this isle: and in the morn
I’ll bring you to your ship and so to Naples,
Where I have hope to see the nuptial
Of these our dear-beloved solemnized;
And thence retire me to my Milan, where
Every third thought shall be my grave.

Alonso |

I long
To hear the story of your life, which must
Take the ear strangely.

Prospero |

I’ll deliver all;
And promise you calm seas, auspicious gales
And sail so expeditious that shall catch
Your royal fleet far off. Aside to Ariel. My Ariel, chick,
That is thy charge: then to the elements
Be free, and fare thou well! Please you, draw near. Exeunt.